A Guide to the James E. Rearden Civil War Collection, 1861-1920
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
James E. Rearden Civil War Collection, 1861-1920
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2007-013
1 half size document box, 0.2 cu. ft.
The Collection is mainly composed of letters written by James E. Rearden to his wife and his mother in the years 1861 and 1862. James Rearden was a Confederate soldier for the Army of the Potomac, 7th South Carolina Volunteer Infantry.
James E. Rearden
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The James E. Rearden Civil War Collection was donated to the Civil War collection at the Special Collections in 2004.
Biographical/Historical Information
James E. Rearden was a confederate soldier with the 7th South Carolina Infantry, a part of Kershaw's brigade known as the "Bloody Seventh" because of heavy losses during numerous battles of the Civil War. James E. Rearden enlisted at Greenville in 1861. His regiment was mainly stationed in the Northern Virginia area where these letters originated. Rearden was promoted to captain in September 1862 and was wounded in the leg at Chickamauga in September 1863. His leg was amputated and he later died of his wounds on September 26, 1863.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of letters written by James Rearden of South Carolina. The majority of the letters are addressed to his wife, Maggie. Some were also sent to his mother and other family members. The letters date from 1861-1862.
Additional materials include two bonds from the 1890s addressed to a Venetia H. Auld and a Commission appointing Donald H. Auld Coroner of Sumter County, South Carolina from 1884. The collection also includes correspondence between W. G. Johnston of Waynesboro, GA and U.S. Aronhalt of Coshocton, OH consisting of three letters regarding the purchase of Airedale puppies dating from 1916, 1917, and 1920. There is an additional letter from the Civil War era, dated September 5, 1864, the author of this letter is unknown.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged chronologically. The letters in folder 8 appear to have been tied together and were roughly in reverse chronological order; they were left in this arrangement in order to preserve original order.
Contents List
- June 15, 1861- July 28, 1861 (Box-folder 1:1)
- August 6, 1861 - August 23, 1861 (Box-folder 1:2)
- September 3, 1861 - September 29, 1861 (Box-folder 1:3)
- October 1, 1861 - October 30, 1861 (Box-folder 1:4)
- November 5, 1861 - November 25, 1861 (Box-folder 1:5)
- December 1, 1861 - December 28, 1861 (Box-folder 1:6)
- January 20, 1862 - October 9, 1862 (Box-folder 1:7)
- January 4, 1862 - September 5, 1862 (Box-folder 1:8)
- Undated Fragments (Box-folder 1:9)
- Additional Materials, 1864-1920
  - Three letters regarding sale of dogs, 1916-1920 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Two South Carolina Bonds, 1895-1897 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Civil War Letter, author unknown, 1864 (Box-folder 1:10)
  - Commission for Coroner of Sumter County, 1884 (Oversize 1)